Guide to the Hedda Morrison photographs, [ca. 1950-1985], 2007-2015
Morrison, Hedda photographs, [ca. 1950-1985], 2007-2015
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Hedda Morrison photographs, [ca. 1950-1985], 2007-2015
4516
Hedda Morrison.
ca. 10 cubic ft.
Photographs, negatives, travel notebooks.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Photographs and negatives of Sarawak, other places in Malaysia, Indonesia, and elsewhere in Southeast Asia.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Hedda Morrison was born Hedda Hammer in Stuttgart, Germany, in 1908. As a young child she contracted polio, which caused her to walk with a limp. In 1929 she completed her secondary education at the Queen Katherine Convent (Königen-Katherina-Stift Gymnasium für Mädchen) in Stuttgart, and was sent to the University of Innsbruck in Austria to study medicine. After a few months she persuaded her parents to allow her to enroll in the State Institute for Photography in Munich (Bäyerische Staatslehranstalt für Lichtbildwesen in München).
After completing her studies, Hedda found paid work difficult to find as a result of the Depression. She decided to travel to China in 1933 in response to an advertisement in a photography journal. Between 1933 and 1938 she managed Hartung's, a German-owned commercial photographic studio in Peking. After her contract there expired in 1938, she continued to work as a freelance photographer. Hedda's photographs of Peking were well known, and she sold many prints and albums to wealthy overseas visitors as souvenirs.
In 1940 Hedda met Alastair Morrison and they married in Peking in 1946. Due to the increasing instability of the political situation in China, they left Peking soon after. The Morrison's spent six months in Hong Kong before relocating to Sarawak, in the north-west of the island of Borneo, where Alastair was appointed to the British Colonial Service and later became a district officer. Throughout her 20-year residence in Sarawak, Hedda accompanied Alastair on all his official journeys and made numerous independent photographic tours. From 1960-66 Hedda was employed by the Sarawak government to work part-time in the photographic section of the Information Office is Kuching. Her duties included taking photographs, establishing a photographic library and training government photographers. Hedda wrote two major books on Sarawak, Sarawak (1957) and Life in a Longhouse (1962).
In 1967 the Morrisons settled in Canberra, Australia. Hedda died in Canberra in 1991, at the age of 82.
Adapted from: "In her view: the photographs of Hedda Morrison in China and Sarawak 1933-67," exhibition catalogue, Powerhouse Museum, Sydney, Australia
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Photographs and negatives of Sarawak, other places in Malaysia, Indonesia, and elsewhere in Southeast Asia.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Morrison, Hedda.
Places:
Sarawak (Malaysia)--Description and travel--Views.; Indonesia--Description and travel--Views.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Negatives.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Travel Notebooks
Boxes 1-2, 28
Series II. Photographs
Boxes 3-16
Series III. Negatives
Boxes 17-25
Series IV. Other Materials
Box 26, 28
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Travel Notebooks
  - Notebooks, 1953, Kelabit II Kelabit Tour I (including Akah) Baram "Men of the Sea: Tropic Shorelife in Sarawak" (notebook and photos) "Fishing Villages" (notebook and photos) Notes, correspondence on Sarawak coast and fish (Box 1)
  - Alastair R.G. Morrison ts. "Travelling Report", 1948 (Box 2)
  - Travel notes, c. 1952, Ngemah Entaba I and II and excursion to Sadok and Lubokantu Penghule Empam II Penghule Banyang Penghule Briak Chendang Sengalang and P. Blaja Entalai Empan I Skudan Siden Chinese tour, 1952 Hardcover notebook: Bakong, Tinjar, Tutoh, Patah (Box 2)
  - Travel notes, visit to 2nd Division, June, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Thailand, Laos, Vietnam, Burma (Nov, Dec 1980) (Box 28)
  - Sarawak, Brunei, Malaysia (June, July 1983) (Box 28)
  - Luzon (Nov, Dec 1981) (Box 28)
  - Indonesia (April, May 1978) (Box 28)
  - Salatiga (Dec 1979-Jan 1980) (Box 28)
  - Ceylon (Nov, Dec 1957) (Box 28)
  - ECAFE, Bangalore (Jan, Feb 1956) (Box 28)
  - Ulu Trusan, Limbang, North Bornea (May, July 1950) (Box 28)
  - Singapore and Malaysia (Feb, March 1967; April, May 1972) (Box 28)
  - Singapore and Malaysia (March, April, 1969/1972) (Box 28)
  - Singapore, Indonesia, Sumatra (April, May 1979) (Box 28)
- Series II. Photographs
  - Photographs, 1974, Solomons (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1980, Vietnam, Laos Monash Madagascar Maratius, Burma (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1980, Philippines Solomons Vietnam, Laos Malaysia Burma (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 1980, Sarawak (contact sheets) Iban, Melugu Gawai Iban, Landdayak, Holt Penan (bound album of prints) (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 1987, Australia Tahiti Korea and Camberra Sarawak coast (Box 6)
  - Photographs, 1987, Sarawak coast (Box 7)
  - Photographs, 1987, Sarawak Reject Land of Hornbill (Box 8)
  - Photographs, 1987, Sarawak (contact sheets) (Box 9)
  - Photographs, 1987, Sarawak (finished prints) (Box 10)
  - Photographs, 1987, Sarawak (contact sheets) (Box 11)
  - Photographs, 1987, Sarawak coast (Box 12)
  - Photographs, 1969, Malaya, Singapore Music Penans (Box 13)
  - Photographs, 1972, Malaysia (Box 14)
  - Photographs, 1983, Malaysia (Box 14)
  - Photographs, 1964, Penan Tutoh, Apoh (Box 14)
  - Photographs, 1967, Thailand, Singapore Malaya, Hong Kong (Box 14)
  - Photographs, 1964, Miri, Sabah (Box 14)
  - Photographs, 1966, Baram (Box 14)
  - Photographs, Indonesia (Box 15-16)
- Series III. Negatives
  - Papua New Guinea, 1968, 2; Museum, Port Moresby Port Moresby, Hibiscus Room Information Office Port Moresby, Koki Market Port Moresby, Radio Port Moresby, General Mt. Hagen Madang Wewak P. Island Regiment Wewak - Maprik Road Maprik Wewak Rabaul (Box 17)
  - Papua New Guinea, 1969, 2; Mt. Hagen Festival, August 30-31 General set, used by Bear Press Mt. Hagen Festival - color Goroka (Box 17)
  - Solomon Islands, 1974, 2; 1 - Guadalcanal: Honiara harbor 2 - Guadalcanal: Honiara landscape 3 - Guadalcanal: Honiara people 4 - Guadalcanal: Honiara war relics 5 - Guadalcanal: Honiara markets 6 - Guadalcanal: Honiara schools 7 - Guadalcanal: Honiara Chinatown 8 - Guadalcanal: Honiara personalities 9 - Malaita: Auki 10 - Malaita: Malun Market 11 - Malaita: Fiu 12 - Malaita: Lilisiana 13 - Malaita: opening of community hall 14 - Malaita: Laulasi 15 - Malaita: roads, landscapes 16 - Gizo: wharf 17 - Gizo: general 18 - Gizo: Gilbertese people 19 - Gizo: Japanese business dealer Sato 20 - Munda: landscape 21 - Munda: installation of new chief 22 - Munda: members of Bentley family 23 - Munda: Kundu burial ground 24 - Munda: small islands nearby 25 - Air views of Solomon Islands 26 - Munda portraits (Box 17)
  - Philippines, Nov. 10-Dec. 11, 1981, 2 (Box 17)
  - Java, Sep. 10-Oct. 2 1972, 3 (Box 17)
  - Indonesia, Apr. 10-May 27 1978, 3; Jakarta Bogor Bandung Train Joyjakarta Surabaya Ujung Pandang Towards Tana Toraja (Box 17)
  - Sumatra, Apr.-May 1978, 3 (Box 17)
  - Bali, May 14-Jun. 6, 1971; 1978, 3; Jalas Putek, 1978 (Box 17)
  - Sumatra, Apr.-May 1978, 3 (Box 17)
  - Singapore, 1955-56, 5; Wau tho General views Street scenes Kelong? Singapore ? Singapore, 1963 (Box 17)
  - Angkor, Cambodia, 5; Angkor Thom Palace, east gate ? Pua Kan Wat Thom Elephant Terrace Circuit Set of enlargements, Angkor Wat Temple (Box 17)
  - Thailand, 5; Bangkok - Bhok Bangkok - general views of streets, temples Thailand file back Chiang Mai market Chiang Mai Hill Temple Chiang Mai? Bangkok Wat Po Bangkok? Bangkok? Market Wat Po Personal Bangkok boathouse? Pat Nam frangipain Bangkok Thai Vet? Bangkok market Bangkok Wai Sutat (Box 17)
  - Malaya, Feb. 1967, 5 (Box 17)
  - Ceylon, 1957, 5 (Box 17)
  - Vietnam, Nov. 20-Dec. 4, 1980, 6 (Box 17)
  - Laos, 6 (Box 17)
  - Burma, 6; Salatiga Sabah (Box 17)
  - India, 1951; Jan. 1956, 7; Kashmir Mt. Abu Darjeeling Udaipur Agra Jaipur Benares Fort Dauladbad Ajanta Ellora Bangalore Ecafe Madras Calcutta Aurangabad (Box 17)
  - Madagascar, 9-C (Box 18)
  - Mauritius, 9-C (Box 18)
  - Sarawak agriculture, 10 (Box 18)
  - Sarawak, Aug. 1987, 11; Kelabits, Marudi, Brunei, Long Jawi, Baram, Belaga (Box 18)
  - Sarawak, 12; small towns (Box 18)
  - Sarawak, 13; Chinese (Box 18)
  - Sarawak, 20-21; Ibans (Box 19)
  - Negatives for books, including Life in a Longhouse, by Hedda Morrison (1962), 22 (Box 19)
  - Land Dayaks, 23 (Box 19)
  - Sarawak, 24; Coastal life (Box 19)
  - Santubong, 14 (Box 20)
  - Malaya, 1969, 1972; Malaysia, 1983; Sabah, 1949, 1972; Brunei 1972; Sarawak, 1972; Singapore, 1972, 25 (Box 20)
  - Melanaus and coastal, 26 (Box 20)
  - Sarawak, 27; Kuching (Box 21)
  - Sarawak, 28; People, events around Kuching (Box 21)
  - Sarawak, 30; Muruts Penans Baram (Box 22)
  - Mt. Hagen (Box 23)
  - "Selected negatives warranting special attention" (Box 23)
  - Salatiga (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 24)
  - Asia, "Selected negatives warranting special attention" (Box 24)
  - Solomon Islands (Box 24)
  - Sumatra, 1979; Philippines, 1981 (Box 25)
  - Indonesia, 1978; Sarawak - color (Box 25)
- Series IV. Other Materials
  - Fair Land Sarawak: Some Recollections of an Expatriate Official, by Alastair Morrison, Studies on Southeast Asia, Southeast Asia Program, Cornell University, 1993 (see also typscript in Box 26) (Box 26)
  - "In her view: the photographs of Hedda Morrison in China and Sarawak 1933-67," exhibition catalogue, Powerhouse Museum, Sydney, Australia (Box 26)
  - Typescript: "Fair Land Sarawak: Some Recollections of an Expatriate Official," by Alastair Morrison, written in Canberra, Australia, June 1976 (Box 26)
  - China and Hong Kong Heritage Calendars, 2007-2010, 2015 (Box 26)
  - Passports (Box 28)
  - Zanana and Sabah posters (Map-case Folder 1)